Ajay Kumar Kaushik

+91 7024335234 *_ajaykaushik396@gmail.com * LinkedIn * GitHub

Profile

An IT professional having 3 years working experience in developing web application and 1 years Data Science projects. Fast learning, results-oriented employee, utilizing organizational skills to drive business goals. Possessing exceptional problem-solving and analytical skills, also have a strong knowledge in Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Data Extraction (Web Scrapping, Web APIs), Machine Learning and Deep Learning model creation.

Data Science Skills

- Python
- Python Libraries: Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn, Seaborn, Matplotlib, TensorFlow, OpenCV
- Machine learning: XGBoost, Cat Boost, Random Forest, Logistic Regression, etc.
- Deep Learning: CNN, RNN (NLP and Computer Vision)
- Tools: PyCharm, Visual Studio, Jupyter Notebook, Google Colab, MS Office
- Database: SQL server, Oracle
- Operating Systems: Windows, Linux, Android
- Version Control: TFS, GitHub

Experience

Programmer Analyst

Cognizant Technology Solutions • Bengaluru, Karnataka

05/2021 - Present

- Designed and developed new enhanced functionality for American International Group (AIG) software applications.
- Provided technical and analytical support for AIG, improving productivity and user experience
- Confirmed program operations by conducting tests and modifying program sequences
- Resolved 2+ Jira tickets per week to optimize and stabilize app performance

Software Engineer

Surya Software Systems Pvt. Ltd • Bengaluru, Karnataka

02/2019 - 06/2021

- Created new employees mentoring program
- Analysing business specification and design technical specification for batch and report, get Approval from team lead
- Wrote, modified, and debugged software for clients
- Design and Developed batch files
- Design and Developing backend logic of reports, show the report using a RDLC (Report Definition language client side)

Education

B. Tech (Computer Science)

CSVTU Bhilai • Bhilai, Chhattisgarh

05/2018

Intermediate

NJS Takhatpur • Takhatpur, Chhattisgarh

05/2014

Certificates

- Machine Learning and Deep Learning Masters (I Neuron)
- Deep Leaning Foundation Certification Training (Udemy)
- Machine Learning- From Basics to Advanced (Udemy)
- Oracle Database Certified (Naresh IT, Hyderabad)

Freelance Project

Cricket Prediction Model for 3D Max India (10/2021 - Present)

 To aim of this project is to build a model that predict the win ratio of playing teams based on a player characteristic, I worked in extracting and transforming the data for modelling

Personal Projects

Customer Segmentation for online retailer

 The aim of this project was to segment the customers into different – different group using unsupervised machine learning methods so that company can give different – different offers to different – different groups of customers based on their previous purchasing behaviors

Movie Recommendation with Sentiments Analysis (09/2021 - 10/2021):

• The aim of this project was to create a movie recommendation same as Netflix or Amazon Prime with Sentiments Analysis of the movie reviews

Virtual Mouse and Voice Control (OpenCV) (11/2021 - 12/2021):

 The aim of this project was to create virtual mouse and voice control, controlled by hand gesture using OpenCV library

Hobbies

- Listening Song
- Computer Gaming
- Travelling
- Trekking